<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Film on 🌀 bledleys blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/film/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Film on 🌀 bledleys blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>copyright 🄯 2025, bledley.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 19:28:41 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/blog/film/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>I&#39;m ditching Letterboxd</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/im-ditching-letterboxd/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 19:28:41 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/im-ditching-letterboxd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had a little time of thinking I could really get into Letterboxd. Over the past few years it seems to have very quickly grown into &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; site for film lovers. I do like reading film reviews from regular people, I was actually quite blown away by just how many movies some people watch. I probably watch one or two films a week personally, sometimes none though, other times I&amp;rsquo;m really into an episodic show or something else takes up my free time.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;does-everything-really-have-to-be-like-social-media&#34;&gt;Does everything really have to be like social media?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The thing about Letterboxd is that to me it feels a little bit like gamification and another form of social media. I feel for some people on there it&amp;rsquo;s a bit of a numbers game, almost a competitive striving to be the most prolific reviewer, a Letterboxd celebrity or influencer. There are lot of reviews that are just simple quippy one liner responses that can be funny but also it just feels like playing for points. They get rewarded with a little thumbs ups, hearts or stars or whatever just like in other familiar addictive services. We&amp;rsquo;re all guilty of it.. we like our little dopamine rewards but does everything really have to become social media?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;im-bad-at-choosing-favourites&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m bad at choosing favourites&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I definitely don&amp;rsquo;t want to come across like I&amp;rsquo;m shitting on the service or people who use it.. I have found some enjoyment in it. If people are getting value out of it and expressing their love of film that&amp;rsquo;s fine by me. It&amp;rsquo;s much more about me personally. First up - I actually find rating things out of 5 very difficult. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t rate many things 5 stars, those would be near perfect, classic &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;send them to space&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; movies. I&amp;rsquo;m thinking  &amp;lsquo;The Godfather: Part 2&amp;rsquo; and the original &amp;lsquo;Alien&amp;rsquo;. I feel like a bit of a tight arse because the majority of things, I rate around 3. A 3 to me is good though! a 3 or 3.5 is - I liked it!. 4 is like, really great! - liked it a lot. Sometimes I like to watch truly terrible 80&amp;rsquo;s movies and get some a lot of enjoyment out of it but how many stars do they deserve? I&amp;rsquo;ve always struggled a bit with favourite lists, a different example, there&amp;rsquo;s so much music I like, too much! I don&amp;rsquo;t think I could possibly narrow it down to a top 5.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;its-not-foss&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not FOSS&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of my other gripes with Letterboxd is that it&amp;rsquo;s quite heavily injected with ads. In a browser with ublock Origin you may not notice or be too bothered by that and if you get a lot of use out the service you could pay for premium to get rid of them.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When setting up my phone on &lt;a href=&#34;https://grapheneos.org/&#34;&gt;GrapheneOS&lt;/a&gt; I carefully vetted which apps I would be allowing onto my device. A look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://exodus-privacy.eu.org/en/&#34;&gt;Exodus&lt;/a&gt; shows that Letterboxd was one of those Android apps that &lt;a href=&#34;https://reports.exodus-privacy.eu.org/en/reports/com.letterboxd.letterboxd/latest/&#34;&gt;contains quite a few trackers&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m trying my hardest to stick with FOSS apps where possible these days and unfortunately Letterboxd doesn&amp;rsquo;t fit the bill. A fully FOSS and privacy respecting Letterboxd alternative could possibly do quite well devs? Using less of these services that require a log in identity and are running nefarious background calls to advertisers on your devices makes me feel happier and much more content.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;have-you-thought-about-just-keeping-a-list&#34;&gt;Have you thought about just keeping a list?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Letterboxd can be useful but have you thought about just keeping a list? I keep track of movies and shows I&amp;rsquo;ve watched in &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/blog/&#34;&gt;Org mode&lt;/a&gt;. A &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;watch.org&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; file, it contains the date and time I watched it. Some have a &lt;em&gt;&amp;rsquo;to watch&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;watched&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; status. When I come across something I might want to watch later I use &amp;lsquo;org capture&amp;rsquo; to dump it into this text file. That works great for me. If I want to write some thoughts about a movie I can do it there or in a blog post. I can look at ratings and other peoples reviews on Letterboxd or any other website without an account if I feel the need to. That&amp;rsquo;s enough for me honestly.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Leave a comment by &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:bledley@posteo.com&#34;&gt;email&lt;/a&gt; or you can find me on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://mastodon.social/@bledley&#34;&gt;Fediverse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
