<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Youtube on 🌀 bledleys blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/youtube/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Youtube on 🌀 bledleys blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>copyright 🄯 2025, bledley.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 11:55:34 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/blog/youtube/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Drawing and Painting in Krita: Youtube</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/drawing-and-painting-in-krita-youtube/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 11:55:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/drawing-and-painting-in-krita-youtube/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I launched my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@bledleysworld&#34;&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt; a little while ago, starting initially with just some time-lapse videos of my digital process. I was trying to just get in the habit of recording, editing, adding some audio and posting online. My first attempt with some kind of vocal commentary was a bit let down by poor audio quality but I think I&amp;rsquo;ve been levelling them up a little each time. I recently got a better quality mic and the last couple seem like something I can share.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/f5pQRD5O4B0&#34;&gt;Part One&lt;/a&gt; of this series I show my process in &lt;a href=&#34;https://krita.org/en/&#34;&gt;Krita&lt;/a&gt; for taking a traditional sketch from your sketchbook, scanning it in and doing digital inks and flats on top.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/2pVRKmWywNw&#34;&gt;Part Two&lt;/a&gt; discusses blocking in a tonal monochrome under painting and hard and soft edges.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m using Krita mostly because this is the easiest way for me to make videos right now. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t say they are totally digital tool specific.. the things discussed are more general art theory that you could apply to other mediums. As for direction of the channel - I&amp;rsquo;m just learning as I go and do like that are many possibilities for the type of content I could make there. I&amp;rsquo;m enjoying the editing process and the medium - YouTube is one of the better and more creative social networks at the moment in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Related: &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/blog/2025-04-19-recent-works-and-update&#34;&gt;Recent works and quick update&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Leave a comment by &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:bledley@posteo.com&#34;&gt;email&lt;/a&gt; or you can find me on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://mastodon.social/@bledley&#34;&gt;Fediverse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
