<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Netlify on 🌀 bledleys blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/netlify/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Netlify on 🌀 bledleys blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>copyright 🄯 2025, bledley.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 11:34:54 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/blog/netlify/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A new theme, a new hope</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/a-new-theme-a-new-hope/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 11:34:54 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/a-new-theme-a-new-hope/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Git submodules? hmmm, sure ok, we&amp;rsquo;ll figure it out..&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Proceeds to break website and spend the rest of the day trying to get it back to some kind of working order]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve changed up my blog theme but woah..holy shit.. it&amp;rsquo;s taken some hours. When building &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; sites the suggested method to install themes is often to use Git submodules.. yeah?.. no?.. no idea. Git stuff stresses me out, I usually stumble through these kind of things following some online documentation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The idea was that I wanted to really strip down my website to look a lot more like these minimalist Bear blogs that I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading a lot of recently.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Why not just use &lt;a href=&#34;https://bearblog.dev/&#34;&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt; itself?.. well I did consider it. My main issue there is that you have to write posts in the browser window. For extra features you&amp;rsquo;ll end up wanting, it becomes a paid subscription service. I like to have the control and to be able to customize every aspect of the site. I want to use my own offline editor to modify the code and write posts in my own writing environment.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Thankfully there is a very nice implementation of the Bear theme by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/janraasch/hugo-bearblog&#34;&gt;janrassch&lt;/a&gt;. I followed instructions to get this set up for Hugo. I copied my pre-existing posts and images across and everything was seemingly up and running nicely.. for a short while at least.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not even sure what happened honestly, but at some point I messed things up badly pushing stuff with git. Skill issue I&amp;rsquo;m sure, but I got to a point where the site wouldn&amp;rsquo;t build and deploy through &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netlify.com/&#34;&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt; and I had no idea how to fix it. It was something to do with tinkering on stuff in the submodule which I now had no idea how to remove.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I used this breakage as an opportunity to generate a fresh directory and Hugo site/Git repo. Turns out this was a good idea. My previous theme was somewhat out of date and would throw errors when you started the server on localhost.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t too difficult to get something fresh up and running, push the repo, connect to Netlify and then link to my custom domain name. A lot of the settings were already in there from the previous build. I opted &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to use the submodule approach this time and just straight clone the theme. I will have to keep track of any major changes but it&amp;rsquo;s given me a good base to work on.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One nice perk to using this theme is that you should see it in light mode/dark mode depending on your system/browser settings. There&amp;rsquo;s definitely some things to do that I&amp;rsquo;m chipping away at. I still don&amp;rsquo;t know how these posts are going to appear in an RSS reader? I want it to show the full posts rather than summaries, pushing this will test that out. I&amp;rsquo;d like to use a custom font and I will be reviewing some past posts and cleaning up a bit. This feels like a fresh start. I&amp;rsquo;d like to do more off the top of the head writing, try to keep things reasonably short form and regular.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Leave a comment by &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:bledley@posteo.com&#34;&gt;email&lt;/a&gt; or you can find me on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://mastodon.social/@bledley&#34;&gt;Fediverse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
